A Guide to the Virginia Anti-Saloon League Collection, 1842-1937
Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library
University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University
Virginia Anti-Saloon League Collection, 1835-1937
University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University
SC 203
2.5 linear feet (3 archival boxes).
John Preston McConnell, first President of Radford University, was an avowed prohibitionist and served as President of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League from 1922-1930. After resigning his post as President of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League he continued as a member of its Executive Committee. McConnell served as a strong financial and moral supporter of the movement until his resignation from the office of President at Radford due to failing health. This collection contains correspondence between McConnell and various Prohibition leaders, politicians, civic and religious leaders, educators, and average citizens as well as newspaper articles, pamphlets, and other publications relating to Prohibition and the activities of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League.
McConnell, John Preston
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the McConnell Family as part of the John Preston McConnell Official Papers
Custodial History
Originally part of the John Preston McConnell Official Papers. Moved to Special Collections and processed by Gene Hyde and Adrian Whicker, 2012.
Biographical Information
John Preston McConnell, first president of Radford University, was a staunch supporter of the prohibition of alcohol. In addition to his tenure as president at Radford, he also served as president of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, a group dedicated to the cause of Prohibition in Virginia, from 1922-1930. During his presidency McConnell corresponded with a number of Prohibition leaders and advocates; he also collected numerous books, articles, and other writings related to the cause of Prohibition. After resigning from the position of president, McConnell continued to be active in the League by donating moral and financial support, stopping only when his health no longer permitted him to continue.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Anti-Saloon League Collection contains numerous letters of correspondence between John Preston McConnell and Virginia Anti-Saloon League leaders, Prohibition leaders, civic and religious leaders, educators, and average citizens, all at local, state, and national levels. These letters reflect on McConnell's sentiments towards the prohibition of alcohol and help shape a better understanding of the activities of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League. These letters were written in the years during and following his role as president of the League and span from 1922-1937.
In addition to correspondence, the collection also contains a number of books, monographs, articles, and other publications printed by the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, the Woman's Christian Temperance Movement, and various other groups and individuals around the United States. The books and monographs span from 1835 to 1931 and discuss topics relating to alcohol consumption and the movement towards alcohol prohibition. The collection contains pamphlets, songs, and articles published by prohibitionists that document the temperance movement and encourage sobriety and the illegalization of alcohol. Additionally, the collection includes various other ephemera relating to the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, the Woman's Christian Temperance Movement, and Prohibition in general.
Arrangement
Series 1: Correspondence, 1910-1937
Series 2: Printed Materials, 1835-1931
Index Terms
McConnell, John Preston, 1866-1941; Anti-Saloon league of Virginia; Prohibition; Virginia, Southwest
Collection Inventory
- Correspondence 1910-1937
  Contains personal correspondence of John Preston McConnell with leaders of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, national and regional prohibition leaders, government officials, Democratic Party officials, citizens, and ministers throughout the Commonwealth of Virginia. Also, contains publications of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, the Woman's Christian Temperance Union of Virginia and other regional and national prohibition groups, as well as newspaper clippings, and ephemera from the period 1910-1937.
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Publications, 1922-1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Publications, 1927-1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Anti-Saloon League Ephemera, 1914-1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Women's Christian Temperence Union Correspondence, 1929-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Printed Materials 1842-1931
  - Pamphlets and Songbook, 1842-1921
    - The philosophy of temperance: an address before the Temperance Society of the University of Vermont, October 18, 1842 by Rev. Zena Bliss, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The battle cry: a new collection of temperance and prohibition songs by H.S. Taylor and Dr. J.B. Herbert, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Life of Charles A. Gunder: saved by the blood from a drunkard's hell, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Can the water be made fine? an essay on Southern politics: primaries, Prohibition, labor, the negro question and remedy by William Henry Gravely, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The philosophy of temperance: an address before the Temperance Society of the University of Vermont, October 18, 1842 by Rev. Zena Bliss, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets and Songbook, 1835-1931
    - Permanent temperance documents of the American Temperance Society, 1835
    - The beautiful life of Frances E. Willard by Anna A. Gordon, 1898
    - Reminiscences of Neal Dow: an autobiography (shelved with Rare Book Collection), 1898
    - The law relating to intoxicating liquors by Howard C. Joyce, 1910
    - Frances Willard: her life and work by Ray Strachey (shelved in Rare Book Collection), 1913
    - Prohibition: modification of the Volstead Law by Lamar T. Beman, 1924
    - The evolution of Prohibition in the United States of America by Ernest H. Cherrington, 1920
    - Anti-Saloon League yearbooks:, 1909-13, 1915, 1917, 1920, 1922-26, 1929-31 1929
    - Andrew Trayton: A Novel of Modern Life by Albert O. Boschen, 1928
    - When at state goes dry: a brief study in law enforcement by Frederick O. Blue, State Tax Commissioner of West Virginia, 1916